This therapy called triple therapy has
been shown in a randomized control trial
to far exceed the current standard for
diabetes treatment. In fact, it's so
effective a prominent diabetes
researcher, Dr. Ralph Defrrono believes
it should be the first line of care. So,
is there any truth to that claim? What
is the triple therapy and why is it so
cheap? I was introduced to triple
therapy through a podcast interview that
I heard Dr. Defranszo give on the Peter
Aia podcast. So instead of me explaining
the details of it, let's listen in on
the bold claims and then we'll pop open
the study and see what the data actually
shows which to me should change the
entire approach to treating diabetes.
It's called the edict study. And in the
edict study, what we did is we used
triple therapy right from the beginning.
And my my my point of the banting
lecture, the ominous octet. If you have
eight problems, and there I'm sure going
to be more to be found and I can give
you a few more if you want. But if you
have eight problems, why in the world do
you think one drug is going to correct
eight problems? It ain't going to happen
in our lifetime. So the point was you
need to use drugs in combination.
So we said we're going to use what and
we uh what we think are the best drugs
at the time. So we started with
metformin with
eenitiide an oldtime GLP1. This is not
the kingpin. This is the pre
luraglutide. Yeah. Exactly. Cuz that's
what was available. That drug was
useless, wasn't it? No, it's a good
drug. Sure. It's not
semlut, but you have to start somewhere,
right? Yeah. Let's let's pay it its dues
as being the gen one OG version of that
drug without which we might not have we
wouldn't have seagglutite. Yes. So it's
kind of an old-timer in and poglitone
that was the triple therapy. Okay. Uh
and then we said every diabetic patient
there 315 people in this study. I
realize they only spoke for a minute but
there's a lot here already. So to
clarify the triple therapy is metformin
eenitide and poglitazone combination. So
Dr. Defranszo is arguing that if you
have a multiaceted disease like
diabetes, it makes little sense to use
just one drug that will only address
part of the problem. And these three
drugs are able to address many concerns
that arise from diabetes. So we'll get
into the data in a moment, but let's
address what these drugs, these
molecules do first. Menformin has been
an extremely popular drug for a long
time now. And it works through a ton of
different mechanisms that we can't go
over now, but simply it inhibits your
liver's ability to release glucose or
sugar into the bloodstream, thereby
reducing your blood sugar burden. On the
other hand, exenide is a molecule that
mimics a hormone in your body and it too
has multiple mechanisms of action.
Chiefly, however, it binds receptors on
the pancreas and stimulates them to
release more insulin. Since insulin then
binds peripheral cells like muscle
cells, kidney cells, and many other
types of cells, it will then take up the
glucose out of the bloodstream, thereby
again reducing blood glucose levels. So
at this point, we have less glucose
going into the bloodstream from the
liver and we have more glucose being
taken out. So a double action. However,
now the third drug poglitazone is a par
gamma activator. That means that the
master protein found in many of our
cells, especially fat cells and muscle
cells called par gamma is activated when
paglitazone molecule diffuses across the
cell membrane and binds directly to par
gamma. So par gamma then travels to the
nucleus of your cells and activates the
expression or production of metabolism
proteins like glute proteins that then
go to the surface of the cell and create
channels for blood glucose to enter the
cells. In addition, par gamma binds
inflammation genes and represses them as
in deactivates them. So through multiple
mechanisms yet again a drug can reduce
diabetes burden. Okay, now that we
understand these drugs a bit better. And
trust me, there's so much more to be
said on each of these, let's get into
the study and why any of this matters.
There 315 people in this study. They're
having insulin clamps, hypoglycemic
clamps, muscle bibs. No one in the world
can do this study. 315 people follow for
six years. Okay. So, we said this is
what we believe is the appropriate
therapy. And then we said we'll use the
ADA approach. The ADA approach is you
start on metformin okay and when you
fail even though not explicitly said the
next drug that's used is
selfuras and then the third drug that's
added is insulin and we said uh that the
goal of therapy was an A1C of 6 and a
half okay uh and that if your A1C uh
rose above 6 and a half uh either on R
triple therapy or on the stepwise treat
to fail approach that the ADA says. ADA
says start metformin, you fail. You add
cell phone, you fail. You add insulin,
you titrate the insulin, basil insulin
up to 60 units. And we said 60 units is
really well, we'll cap it because yeah,
you're already at 2x physiologic. Yeah.
And that now you have to now split the
dose of insulin. You have to be adding
rapid acting insulin. I I think this is
quite reasonable. Six years later,
okay, 29% of the people with the ADA
approach have failed. Their A1C is above
six and a half. Six years later, with
our approach, 70% of the people have an
A1C that's less than 6 and a half. Why?
Insulin clamp huge improvement with our
therapy. Okay, this is the eating study.
The the three-year data published the
six-year data. We're writing it out. How
much improvement in insulin sensitivity
with the ADA approach? Zero. Okay. So,
the ADA or the diabetes association has
a standard treatment of metformin first
and then when it begins to fail to
control diabetes, add a sulfonal ura
drug, something that we haven't
discussed. And when that fails, start
adding more and more insulin to force
the cells to take up glucose and keep
blood glucose levels stable. This triple
therapy approach attacks the issue with
a powerful opening salvo to knock
diabetes on its heels and decimate its
troops. That explained, is that actually
what happened in the edict study? Well,
here it is. These are the three-year
results because the six-year results
haven't been published yet. The aim is
to keep HBA1C, so a marker of glycation,
which is a fancy term for glucose
molecules bound to proteins and cell
membranes, reducing their functionality.
The higher the number, the worse.
Anyway, the goal is to keep this number
less than 6.5%, which is no longer
diabetic, but pre-diabetic. not perfect,
but if people go above 6.5%, they're
considered a failure and shunned by
society until they go out in the world
and prove themselves and are then
invited back to their high school
reunion where they give a speech about
never giving up even when your teachers
don't believe in you. Okay, maybe that
analogy went a bit off the rails, but
the main point is if they are deemed
diabetic again, it's marked as a fail by
the intervention, the standard ADA
intervention or the triple therapy. So,
what happened? If we pop open the first
bit of data, we can see the three years
on the horizontal axis and the HBA1C on
the vertical. Remember, if that goes up,
that's bad. Clearly, both interventions
worked really well at dropping HBA1C
immensely. But you can see that over
time the average HBA1C for the triple
therapy is less than six and the
conventional ADA intervention is
hovering around that fail line of 6.5
over the 3 years. In addition, if we
doubleclick I just triggered a bunch of
consultants on the triple therapy and
look at its effectiveness based on where
people start in their diabetes. We can
see that even if a person starts at very
high around a 10 or higher HBA1C, the
triple therapy is still able to crush
HBA1C to around six. It seems highly
effective no matter your starting point.
To be fair, the same result is also seen
with the conventional treatment. So,
both therapies beat back diabetes
significantly. But what about the actual
failure rate? as in what was the risk of
hitting 6.5% or higher over time and
what else changed that might indicate an
overall improvement in health from one
therapy over the other. We'll get into
it, but I'd like to also mention that
there's information on the effects on
the pancreas, the insulin releasing
hormone, and on plaque in the arteries,
which was also assessed by the
researchers, including some additional
details that we won't have time to get
into here, but I do include them in the
extended version of this video and
research review. If you're interested in
full access, be sure to join Aphysionic
Insiders. And by the way, this also
includes live sessions with me and an
exclusive community, a private podcast,
and more. The link is in the description
box. The failure rate data is shown
here. This is a Kaplan Meyer plot. So,
if the lines are higher, that's better.
It means that fewer people failed.
Clearly, the triple therapy had a lower
failure rate. The exact amount is
roughly 33%. Yet, the conventional
therapy had a failure rate closer to
60%. And why might that discrepancy be
there? In day-to-day measurements, can
we foreshadow the difference between the
therapies? Well, yes. Here we're looking
at two measurements based on an oral
glucose tolerance test, which is simply
an experiment where participants consume
a set amount of sugar and the
researchers measure what happened to
their blood glucose and insulin levels.
Those are the two measurements. On top
we're seeing the blood glucose and on
the bottom we see the blood insulin
levels. The left side is the
conventional therapy and the right side
is the triple therapy. We see a baseline
measurement that's 3 years ago before
diabetes was treated and the white dots
are the after treatment. If we look at
the bottom measurement first, insulin or
more specifically ceptide which is the
product of the cleaving of immature
insulin molecule into its mature form.
For the most part, insulin rises around
the same for baseline and 3 years later
for either therapy. Technically, there
are some nuances to discuss here too,
but we just don't have time and it takes
away from our objective of understanding
this. No doubt though, the biggest
difference is the top data, the blood
glucose. It's evident that the
conventional therapy reduces blood
glucose, but it still rises
substantially. However, the triple
therapy is extremely effective at
keeping blood glucose lower after
consuming sugar. This speaks when
insulin levels are roughly the same to
insulin sensitivity. Insulin sensitivity
is simply put when the insulin molecule
binds to your peripheral cells as we
described earlier. there's a stronger
activation of the cell to allow blood
glucose into the cell. So per molecule
of insulin, you're taking in more
glucose, thereby removing glucose from
the bloodstream, and that's a good
thing. So the better one's insulin
sensitivity, the less diabetes. The
researchers used an index based on data
that we just went over with the oral
glucose tolerance test called a Matsuda
index. Here we see the two therapies
with baseline and three years later. If
insulin sensitivity goes up, that's a
good thing. And it likely doesn't need
annunciating, but insulin sensitivity
only improved with the triple therapy,
indicating it likely improves whole body
insulin sensitivity and therefore uses
that to lead to better results than the
conventional therapy, which does not
improve insulin sensitivity. That's a
huge win in favor of the triple therapy
approach. Okay. Now a bit of context to
add to this all before we break it down
very simply. First is as always the case
it this is just one study and although
Dr. DeFranzo is likely highly respected
in his field the study was not blinded.
So the researchers and the participants
were aware of what they were taking.
This could introduce bias. Second, there
were some side effects of the drugs,
especially in the conventional therapy
because adding insulin at the end can
lead to hypoglycemia, meaning too low
blood sugar. Third, some people gained
weight and some people lost weight over
the 3 years. However, regardless if a
person lost or gained weight, triple
therapy outperformed conventional
therapy. Fourth, anytime drugs are the
subject, people retaliate with
pitchforks demanding a mention of diet
and exercise. So, allow me to mention
that the discussion of one does not
exclude the other. The discussion is
around this therapy, which did not
include lifestyle modification. But no
doubt many diabetes related benefits can
be had through lifestyle modification
even without said side effects. It just
isn't the topic of this study. But I'll
acknowledge it before I get sent to the
goolog. So where does that leave things?
Well, Dr. Defranszo is right that the
edict study clearly shows after 3 years
that the triple therapy of metformin,
eenitide, and poglytoone is better than
the conventional step-wise introduction
used in usual care. So, if you've been
newly diagnosed with diabetes and
lifestyle changes are not an option,
consider discussing the triple therapy
option with your physician. I'd also add
that there are other ways of handling
diabetes like those mentioned in this
next video.
[Music]
[Applause]